so let's compare what we can get from a
multi core versus single core processor
in a new technology suppose that in the
previous technology generation we got a
processor that has an area of 2
centimeters squared
it was achieving 2.5 instructions per
cycle and it consumed a hundred watts at
two gigahertz frequency and this is the
highest power that we can allow this
processor to have and this hundred watts
is what we can reasonably cool now let's
say we get a new technology where the
same exact processor would be half the
area because our transistors have shrunk
because it's the same design it's going
to have the same IPC and because
transistors have shrunk we also reduce
the power of this processor when
operating at the same two gigahertz
frequency as before now of course
because this processor is smaller in the
new technology than in the old one if we
want to do the best we can with two
centimeter square we have two options
our first option is a better single core
processor this processor will be
designed to occupy the entire area that
we have which is 2 centimeters square
it's a more complicated processor that
allows us to achieve a IPC of 3.5 so it
executes 3.5 instructions per cycle not
2.5 as the old processor but because
it's a fancier processor and has more
transistors it spends 75 watts when
operating at 2 gigahertz so the question
for you is first if we allow this
processor to spend all hundred watts
that we can call what is the frequency
it can get in gigahertz and if we do
that what is the speed up this better
single core achieves versus what we can
get in the old technology the second
option we have in this new technology is
to simply put two cores on this chip so
it's going to be two cores like this
this is going to get us 2 centimeters
squared
IPC is going to be 2.5
on each core and each core is going to
consume 50 watts at two gigahertz so we
get our entire budget spent by having
this course operated two gigahertz so
the question for you here is what's the
speed-up of this two core approach
versus the old technology assuming of
course that the old work can simply be
divided among the course so pretty much
having two cores allows us just to split
the same work that we had before onto
two cores without adding any new
instructions and without sacrificing the
IPC